## Ben Schulz

# Software Engineer

**\( \text{\text{benschulz.dev}} \)** 

• BenGSchulz

in BenGSchulz

✓ mail@benschulz.dev

**4** 307-413-8377

Seattle, WA

#### **SUMMARY**

Frontend Engineer with 5 years of experience transforming complex ideas into user-centered products using TypeScript, Angular, and React in enterprise-scale applications and fast-paced startup environments. I take ownership of projects from design to deployment and beyond, driving high impact initiatives that significantly improve performance, accessibility, and code maintainability while fostering feedback ecosystems. Combining technical expertise with collaborative communication, I build maintainable systems that prioritize both end-user experience and developer workflow through comprehensive testing and documentation. I am eager to apply my skills to solve meaningful problems as part of a team that values continuous learning and quality-driven development.

## **SKILLS**

- Languages: TypeScript, JavaScript, HTML, CSS, Java, C++
- Frontend: Angular, RxJS, React.js, Next.js, Tailwind, Webpack, esbuild
- Testing: WebDriverIO, Jasmine, Jest, Enzyme, Testing Library
- Backend: Node.js, Express, REST APIs, PostgreSQL, MongoDB
- Tools: Git, GitHub, Zsh, Jenkins, Jira, Confluence, Figma

## **EXPERIENCE**

## **Nextworld**, *Software Engineer 2* - Denver, CO

Nov 2019 - Jun 2024

- Built expertise in Angular, TypeScript, and RxJS to drive product direction and execution of sustainable, feature-rich UI components and scalable, event-driven systems powering a no-code enterprise application platform.
- Spearheaded long-term re-architecture of crucial features such as datatable infrastructure, advanced filtering components, and multistep forms with a focus on improving performance, capabilities, and code standards.
- Achieved 2x improvement to LCP and reduced technical debt by modernizing legacy templating middleware into reusable and extensible components.
- Exponent of intensive testing culture to achieve improved code quality, using Jasmine + WebdriverIO to build comprehensive suites and additionally implementing recorded interactions for no-code test automation.
- Improved critical filtering response times by 30% after partnering with backend team to design and uptake enhanced API methods with a huge reduction in payload size.
- Maintained WCAG AA standards and i18n compliance in all my work to ensure inclusivity across the platform, particularly identified the need for and implemented a standardized keyboard navigation framework for multifaceted interfaces.
- Recognized as a "go-to" team member and project lead by mentoring junior engineers, driving pair programming and code review sessions, and building a healthy feedback culture among cross-functional teams.

## **Spotpost**, *Software Development Intern* - Denver, CO / Remote

Feb 2019 - Jul 2019

- Built a digital advertisement and bulletin board platform from the ground up with a cross-functional team.
- Designed RESTful API methods and implemented the frontend authentication flow using React + JWT, ensuring secure user access.
- Proposed new product features, technologies, and process optimizations to improve team efficiency and product quality.

## **DSST Public Schools**, *Creative Coding Elective Teacher* - Denver, CO

Aug 2018 – Nov 2018

- Designed a trimester curriculum focused on creative coding and CS fundamentals using OpenProcessing/p5.js: Class Page.
- Cultivated interest in my passion to use coding for creative expression and human-computer interaction.
- Evolved my leadership and mentoring skills through instruction and collaboration with 38 students, grades 9 11.

### **PROJECTS**

## Personal Advocate Chatbot

- Built my own professional advocate using RAG powered by Next.js, Vercel AI + OpenAI, and Neon Postgres + Drizzle ORM.
- Utilized prevector and OpenAI embeddings API for efficient content embedding, enabling real-time contextual conversations.
- Designed a fluid interface using Tailwind CSS and Motion animations, ensuring an engaging user experience.
- Leveraged SSR and streaming to optimize performance and SEO with quick-to-load, indexable pages.

### **EDUCATION**